<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The declaration of the Lord Generall of the army of the confederat Catholicks in the province oft Leinster</title>
            <author>Tara, Thomas Preston, Viscount, 1585-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09774</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3314</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R182046</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">62369606</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 62369606</idno>
            <idno type="VID">188093</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09774)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 188093)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2855:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The declaration of the Lord Generall of the army of the confederat Catholicks in the province oft Leinster</title>
                  <author>Tara, Thomas Preston, Viscount, 1585-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Kilkenny :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Preston. Cf. Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>"[Pr]inted by Command of the councell and congregation in the yeare 1646."</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: broadside tightly bound with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tara, Thomas Preston, --  Viscount, 1585-1655.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1625-1649 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Politics and government --  17th century --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:188093:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE DECLARATION THE LORD GENERALL OF THE ARMY OF THE CONFEDERAT CATHOLICKS IN THE PROVINCE OFT LEINSTER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas vpon the late Deſigne on Dublin I was tranſported with a particular deſire of aduancing his Majeſties ſeruice, and preſeruing thoſe Parts from the deſtruction that commonly waits on the chance of warre, to entertaine <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reaty with the Lord Marqueſſe of Clanrickard not doubting to obtaine by his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>s meanes, ſuch conditions for the Confederat Catholicks, as might render the <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ngdome ſatisfied, And after ſome time ſpent in the conſideration of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>s of that engagement, I acquainted the Councell and Congregation therewith, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> on a more ſtrict Examination thereof, hauing taken to conſideration the law in <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>e againſt Catholick Religion in this Kingdome found the contents of that enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ment in many eſſentiall points to be short of the libertie and freedome requiſit in <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> free exerciſe of the Catholick Religion, and the ſafetie of the liues and fortunes of Confederat Catholicks, as by the Councell and Congregations obſeruations on that engagement may more euidently appeare, upon aduertiſement whereof I held my ſelfe <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ged by the oath of vnion which I had ſworne, and by the faith I ought to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> to recede from the treaty, if the obiections againſt that Engagement were not ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> by enlargement of further Grants that might ſatisfie the Councell and Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>. And moreouer to take from me all hopes of any Concluſion that way, I found <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> contrary to the ſaid engagement a reſolution was taken not to receiue any of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y vnder my command to Garizon in Dublin and other principall Garizons vnder <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> maieſties obedience that being the chiefe point granted me for the ſecuritie of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d engagement, ſo as I mainely miſtruſted there was no good intention towards the <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nfederat Catholicks either in the matters granted or in the ſecuritie thereof, ſeeing <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en in the uery firſt entrance an apparent breach of the promiſe contained in that <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gagement, ſo as it ſtood neither with honor nor ſecuritie I should rely on that enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ment. Being therefore compelled to deſist from further proceeding therein, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rdingly withdrew the forces vnder my command to the Quarters deſigned for them <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> order of the Councell and Congregation. yet leaſt any should be misled by an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the continuance of that Treatie or any concluſion thereupon, I thought good <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot finding any thing in the whole conduct of that affaire whereby the innocency of <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y actions may not be generally acknowledged) to publish this declaration, that all the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onfederat Catholicks may be thereby forewarned to ſtand on their owne defence againſt the aduerſe Party, and not to inſiſt or rely on any Conditions but, ſuch as by authority of the Councell and Congregation, or of the Generall Aſſembly shall be ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>led, that being the whole ſcope of my intention in the late treaty, notwithſtanding any miſconſtruction to the Contrary, which I deſire may bey ſo vnderſtood, whereby the perfect union of the Confederate Catholikes may have full ſettlement, and my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ntion heareby declared not to adhere to any other reſolution or Vnion.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Waterford <date>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 22th of December 1646.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>T. PRESTON</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed by Commaund of the Councell and Congregation in the yeare 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
